Guide to the Guerlac-Perrin Lavoisier Archive, 1939-1987.
Guerlac-Perrin Lavoisier Archive
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Guerlac-Perrin Lavoisier Archive, 1939-1987.
4710
Guerlac, Henry.
6.5 cubic feet and 74 notebooks;
Photocopies, photographs, microfilm, manuscripts, computer media, and research materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Notes on manuscript sources for the study of French chemist Antoine Laurent Lavoisier, compiled by American historians of science Henry Guerlac, Carl Perrin, and Rhoda Rappaport.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Notes on manuscript sources for the study of French chemist Antoine Laurent Lavoisier, compiled by American historians of science Henry Guerlac, Carl Perrin, and Rhoda Rappaport. Includes notes on contemporaries of Lavoisier and transcriptions of passages from manuscripts. Scientists investigated include Lavoisier, Jean-Antoine-Claude Chaptal, Antoine-François de Fourcroy, Pierre Joseph Macquer and his Dictionnaire de chimie, and Philippe-Frédéric baron de Dietrich, Jean Senebier, Torbern Bergman, Joseph Black, Carl Wilhelm Scheele, Johann Theodor Eller, Louis Bernard Guyton de Morveau and his Elemens de chimie théorique et pratique. Also included are notes on minutes of meetings of the Académie des sciences (France) in the late 18th century.
Libraries consulted include the Académie des Sciences (France), Bibliothèque Nationale de France, Bibliothèque de la Sorbonne, Archives Nationales (France), Museum d'histoire naturelle, Bibliotheek of the Rijksuniversiteit te Leiden, British Library, and others.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Guerlac, Henry.; Chaptal, Jean-Antoine-Claude, comte de Chanteloup, 1756-1832.; Chaptal, Jean-Antoine-Claude, comte de Chanteloup, 1756-1832; Dietrich, Philippe-Frédéric, baron de, 1748-1793.; Dietrich, Philippe-Frédéric, baron de, 1748-1793; Fourcroy, Antoine-François de, comte, 1755-1809.; Fourcroy, Antoine-François de, comte, 1755-1809; Guyton de Morveau, Louis-Bernard, 1737-1816.; Guyton de Morveau, Louis-Bernard, 1737-1816; Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, 1743-1794.; Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, 1743-1794; Macquer, Pierre Joseph, 1718-1784.; Macquer, Pierre Joseph, 1718-1784.; Macquer, Pierre Joseph, 1718-1784; Perrin, Carl.; Rappaport, Rhoda, 1935-; Scheele, Carl Wilhelm, 1742-1786.; Scheele, Carl Wilhelm, 1742-1786; Académie des sciences (France); Archives nationales (France); Bibliothèque de la Sorbonne.; Bibliothèque nationale (France); British Library.; Museum d'histoire naturelle (Paris, France); Rijksuniversiteit te Leiden. Bibliotheek.
Subjects:
Chemistry -- History -- Sources.; Chemistry
Form and Genre Terms:
History; Sources
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Henry Guerlac
Boxes 1-4; 7-8
Microfilm
Research materials relating to Lavoisier Bibliography
Miscellaneous Research
Lavoisier: Manuscripts Offered for Sale
Materials relating to Lavoisier Archives
Lists
Photographs of Manuscripts (uncatalogued)
Académie des Sciences
Archives Nationales
Biblioteque De Clermont-Ferrand
Biblioteque De l'Institit
Cornell University
Jozerand
Various Archives and Libraries
Photostat Negatives (with original numbering)
Lavoisier Reprints
By Author
Precursors & Contemporaries
Topical Background
Bibliographical Notecards
Series II. Carl Perrin
Boxes 5-6
Microfilm
Computer Disks and Punch Cards
Computer Disks
Punch Cards
Research materials relating to Lavoisier Bibliography
Series III. Research Notebooks
Cataloged Separately
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Henry Guerlac
  Items with 18th and early 19th Century dates within the collection are copies and refer to the original dates of publication or creation.
  - Microfilm
    - Isaac Newton: Opticks, 1704 (with additional MS material), 1704 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Miscellaneous papers of Academies Des Sciences in Biblioteque Nationale, September 1773 (Box 1, Reel 2)
      "Verification des expériences de M. Lavoisier sur la fixation de l'ais daus…" Sept. 1773
    - British Museum (Box 1, Reel 3)
    - Biblioteque Nationale Lavoisier M35 (Box 1, Reel 4)
      Includes correspondence with Ellen B. Wells, underlined "atrocious signatures" to label reel
    - Journal de Medecine, vol 33 (complete) (Box 1, Reel 5)
      Includes subject-author index for first 65 volumes and correspondence with Ellen B. Wells
    - De Calore (Box 1, Reel 6)
    - Opticks by Isaac Newton (from MIT), October 4, 1730 (Box 1, Reel 7)
    - Vol. 7 of Lavoisier's registres, Archives of Académie des Sciences, November 1782-1784 (Box 1, Reel 8)
    - Atlas Mineralogique (Box 1, Reel 9)
    - Foreign Correspondence (Box 1, Reel 10)
      Label is hard to read.
    - From the Royal Society of London (Box 1, Reel 11)
    - Laval Voyage (Box 1, Reel 12)
    - Unlabelled Microfilm Reel (Box 1, Reel 13)
    - Unlabelled Microfilm Reel (Box 1, Reel 14)
    - From the Royal Society of London (Box 1, Reel 15)
    - Series IV #1: Archives Nationales (Box 1, Reel 16)
    - BPD 4795 - From Oxford University Press (Box 1, Reel 17)
    - Dossiers 1324, 1326, 1335-37, 1341, 1346 (Box 1, Reel 18)
      Laplace-4, Brisson-2, Trudaine-1, Bucquet-1, Guylon-1
    - 23, 19 diagram, 28, 66 (Box 1, Reel 19)
    - E. McDonald; Jean Baptiste Michele Bucquet (Box 1, Reel 20)
    - Empty Box -- Second addition é la dé….eiation préseutée eui… (Box 1)
    - Kodak box -- 5 rolls of microfilm (Box 1)
      Labelled volume 10-13 and one unlabeled
    - Wooden Box: Guerlac's Research, Series I (Box 1)
    - Wooden Box: Guerlac's Research, Series II (Box 1)
    - Cardboard Box of loose microfilm rolls and clippings (Box 1)
  - Research materials relating to Lavoisier Bibliography
    Secondary literature, correspondence, drafts, xeroxes, etc.
    - Henry Guerlac - Short Biography, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Hand-written notes (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Includes a family tree of Jacques Paulze.
    - Chronology of Lavoisier (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - A Chronology of Lavoisier's Career (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - M. Berthelot: Discourse on Lavoisier (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Birembaut: "Quelques aspects de la personnalite de Lavoisier", 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Includes other manuscripts by Birembaut
    - William Brande on Lavoisier in: A Manual of Chemistry (copies), 1819, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Cuvier: article "Lavoisier" from Michaud: Biographie Univer. (copies) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Fourcroy: "Notice sur Lavoisier", Lalande: "Notice sur Lavoisier" (copies) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Rabbe: Biographie Universelle et Portative des Contemporains Article "Lavoisier" (copy), 1836 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Abbé Terray" in Pierre Clément: Portraits Historiques (copy), 1855 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Lavoisier and the Revolution (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Lavoisier's Library, September 26, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Correspondence between Ellen Wells and Prof. H. Guerlac regarding Cornell University collection
    - Hand-written notes and "Why Was Lavoisier Beheaded?" a term paper by Karl Nell (1953), 1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
      In legal sized folder.
    - "Lavoisier", an essay by Dan Marvin (copy), April 8, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Dr. Cabanès: (1) "A qui doit on imputer la mort de Lavoisier"; (2) "La Republique m'a pas Lesoin de Savants"; (3) "Une infirmerie prison pendant la Terreur" (copies) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Review (unpublished) of Lavoisier Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence related to Lavoisier Book, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Correspondence between Cornell and Guerlac, royalty reports
    - Reviews of "Lavoisier, the Crucial Year", 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - The Chemical Revolution: A Word from Monsieur Fourcroy", 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Includes correspondence between Bernard Cohen and Henry Guerlac
    - Observations sur la Physique: "Extrait d'un Mémoire lu par M. Lavoisier…sur la nature de l'Eu, & sur des expériences qui paroissent prouver que cette substance n'est point élément proprement dit…" (copy), December 1783 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Collection académique and References to Ellen and Veirel(?) Russians exczec(?) on Neiciuy(?) (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Effervescence -- Lavoisier & Gaujon, December 1769 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Copy of Journal des Sçavans with notes
    - "Précis de la doctrine de M. de Morveau" Observations 2 p. 281-291 (copy), October 1773 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Review of Duveen Bib. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Notes primarily regarding books for research (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Nouvelles" -- a review of recent work on analyses and synthesis of water, and its implications. J. de Medicine 61 pp. 429-431 (copy) (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - David Portrait of Lavoisier, 1788, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Includes correspondence from William A. Bayless
    - Preface to Mme. Lavoisier traducieur (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Physico-Chymie Théorique, Endialogue, par M.L.J. Decroix, a review from J. de Médecine vol 61 pp. 104-6 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Le Defenseur des Opprimés ou le Francais Impartiale (From Auland Collection -- Harvard) (copy), 1790 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "Discours sur le Phlogistique" Observations 3 p. 185-200, 1774 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Sur la nature du principe, etc. Rozier's Journal, 1775 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Carozzi on Lavoisier's Geology, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      The Ohio Journal of Science, volume 65
    - Alexander Crum Brown: "The development of the idea of chemical composition" (copy), 1897 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Crosland: "Lavoisier's Theory of Acidity", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - J.B. Dumas to the Pli casleié, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      Includes correspondence between J. Bentley and Henry Guerlac
    - Fric: "Contribution à l'évolution des idées de Lavoisier sur la nature de l'air et sur la calcination de métaux" and notes, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Lavoisier on Respiration (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Jerry Gough: Articles and Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Kohler on Lavoisier and Combustion, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Mason: Graphic Formulas in Organic Chemistry, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - E. McDonald: "The Collaboration of Bucquet and Lavoisier", June 1966 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Douglas Mckie: "Antoine Laurent Lavoisier, F.R.S." Notes and Records 7 (1949) pp. 1-41, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Meldrum: "Three Notes on Combustion" (copy), 1932 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Meldrum: "Lavoisier's Early Work in Science" - Part I and Part II (copy), 1934 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Robert J. Morris, Jr.: Articles, June 1972 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Reply to Morris, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Pattison Muir: Heroes of Science article "Lavoisier" (copy), 1883 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Multhauf (on Gunpowder): The French Crash Program for Saltpeter Production, 1776-94, April 1971 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Payen on Powder (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Perrin - unpublished papers of 1973, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Perrin, Carl - Prelude to a Theory of Calcination (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Perrin - Anonymous article regarding Phlogiston (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Perrin - Method and Metaphysics in Lavoisier's Table of the Elements (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Rappaport: "The early disputes between Lavoisier and Monnet" (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - "Avis sur les Leçons de Chymie de feu M. Roulle" -- Journal de Médecine vol. 33 pp. 381-2 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Mario Roustan: "Lavoisier et l'éducation nationale", September 1927 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Smeaton & Fourcroy: Articles and Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - M. Speter: "Lavoisier und seine Vorläufer", 1910 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Gunpowder in America from The American Historical Review, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Thackray -- notes from his thesis regarding Lavoisier, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous Research
    - The Lavoisier Papers, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Boerhaave: Articles and Correspondence, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Lavoisier and Electricity (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Lavoisier Memoirs abstract ed. I -- Mem. sur la combustion en général, 1777-1779 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Metzger: Philosophie de la Matiére chez Lavoisier, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Paneth: Concept of Element, May 1962 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - R. Taton: "A propos de l'oeuvre de Monge en physique" (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Chemistry as a Branch of Physics -- collaboration of Lavoisier and Laplace, 1787, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Hand-written Notes (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Guyion de Morveau (copy), 1806 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Calorimeter - Notes on Lavoisier on Respiration (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Use of Word "Gas" (notes) (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Designations of Oxygen (Lavoisier) (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Lavoisier - Laplace - Memoir of 1793 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Mémoire sur la Chaleur (copies), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Mémoire sur la Chaleur (correspondence), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Lavoisier Mémoir abstract ed. "Unes générales sur la calorique" in Memoire de Chimie (notes), 1792 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Matiere du feu (notes), 1777 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Negatives from Illustrations (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Correspondence, Xeroxes, 1956, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
      Includes copy of "Traite de Physique Experimentale et Mathematique" by J.B. Biot
    - "Chemistry as a Branch of Physics: Laplace's Collaboration with Lavoisier" (Box 2, Folder 84)
      Notations in the margins.
    - Lavoisier Manuscripts Offered for Sale
      - Madame Lavoisier, 1951-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Lavoisier Exposition: Paris, Lycée Lavoisier, 1967 (comm. By Steve Jacobs), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Lavoisier Leiker(?), 1774, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        Copies of manuscripts
      - Lavoisier Letters, 1789-1791, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        Correspondence and listing only
      - Kraus -- Important Works in the field of Science, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Materials relating to Lavoisier Archives
    - Lists and Procedures
      - Lavoisier Project -- Cornell-Paris contacts, April 1982, April 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Lavoisier -- Manuscripts Recataloguing project, August 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Manuscripts: Cataloguing and Indexing Procedures (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - List of Documents in Eleutherian Mills Historical Library, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Lavoisier Documents (Guerlac): Punchcard Keysort Classification Code (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Microfilms -- Russian (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - List of Microfilms in Series III -- Duveen Collection (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - List of Microfilms; Series IV (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Documents to Order (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Manuscripts and Microfilms (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Photographs of Manuscripts (uncatalogued)
      - Museum d'Histoire Naturelle MS 1929 IV 3 "Catalogue d'une belle collection de mines", 1929 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Museum d'Histoire Naturelle MS 1929 IV 5 Letter from Pierre to Lavoisier (18 May 1765), 1765, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Museum d'Histoire Naturelle MS 1929 IV 4 Letter from Chavoyer to Lavoisier (30 Sept. 1767), 1797, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Museum d'Histoire Naturelle MS 1996, 27 Letter from Dalloz to Lavoisier (30 August 1784), 1784, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Museum d'Histoire Naturelle MS 1996, No 91 Letter from Perruchon de Longeville to Lavoisier (9 June 1788), 1788, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Académie des Sciences 1670 Bm & Bn sur les élemens (1766), 1766 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - #1385 Reflexions sur les expériences qu'on peut tenter à l'aide du mirior ardent, 1772 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Lavoisier & Macques report on Mitouard's memoir on destruction of diamond, 1792 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Macquer & Lavoisier report on Mitouard's distillation of phosphorous, 1772 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Archives Nationales MS (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Archives Nationales AEii 1014, 1774 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Besançon -- Bibliotheque Mun. MS 1442 fols 19, 20. Report to the Academy on an Observation of M. Hesmann (9 June '73), 1773, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Biblioteque De Clermont-Ferrand MS 337 fols 276-7 "Memoir pour le Dupain-Triel", 1771 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Biblioteque De Clermont-Ferrand MS 337 fol 404, 1814 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Biblioteque Nationale N.A. Fr. 1305 fol. 149; Letter to Parisis, fils (20 7bre 1792), 1792 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Biblioteque Nationale N.A. Fr. 3258 fol 145-129, Reports to the Academy, 1786 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Museum D'Histoire Naturelle MS 1929 IV, I; Letter from Deperthuis to Lavoisier; 11 (or 14) July 1765, July 1765 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Museum D'Histoire Naturalle MS 1929 IV, 2; Letter from Jaur to Lavoisier; 21 Dec. 1767, December 21, 1767 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Académie des Sciences
      - Procés-verbaus of Academie, 1772-1783, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Films ordered from Académie des Sciences, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Académie des Sciences, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Items Missing from the Academie, 1965, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Académie des Sciences (Box 3, Folder 38)
        List of items to check at the Academy
      - Académie des Sciences Order List (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - "Physique Soloité des corps" MSS Ac. Sci. 1670 Bo, 1768 (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Procès-Verbaux: Sept. 1774-Dec.1774, September-December 1774 (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Procès-Verbaux 1778, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Academy of Science #380 (excerpt): "Commencement d'un Traité de Chimie" (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Bibllioteque de L'Ecoles des Mines: Elitherian Mills Historical Library, 1785, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Archives Nationales
      - Documents at Archives Nationales, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 45)
        Correspondence between Guerlac and Jacob Price
      - Lavoisier's Legal Transactions; Archives Nationales M.C. XCIX rép. 6, 1782-1794 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Biblioteque de Clermont-Ferrand
      - Contents of Microfilm #43, Series II (1939), 1939 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - Letter from Lavoisier to d'Ormesson, 28 May 1788 (from microfilm #43, documents at La Caniére, 1939), 1788, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - Biblioteque de Clermont-Ferrand MS 337, fol 158; Letter from Durfont de Ciurac probably to Lavoisier (Mars 1773), March 1773 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Biblioteque de l'Institut
      - 2 Letters: Lavoisier to Hennin; Biblioteque de l'Institut, Fonds Hennin MS 1266 folders 74-75, 1786-1787 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Letter: Commissioners of the National Treasury to Lessart; Biblioteque de l'Institut Collection Paltier-Laurent, 1791, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Cornell University
      - Booklet for "Antione Laurent Lavoisier: An Exhibition", 1963 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - Lavoisier Documents (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - Lavoisier Collection, 1963, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Lavoisier documents of Duveen left to Cornell 1960-1962, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - Lavoisier Collection (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - LaForic Collection, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Jozerand
      - Inventory of Fonds Chabrol (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - La Caniere letters, xerox copies from H.G. 1939 Notebook III, 1785-1788 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - Documents at la Caniére (the lost letters); xeroxed from H.G. 1939 Notebook III, 1782 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      - Material en Elerge of Guellard -- rouds Chabrel (Box 3, Folder 62)
      - Outline of "Système sur les élémens", August 1772, August 1772 (Box 3, Folder 63)
      - Photos from Fouils Chabul (Box 3, Folder 64)
      - 317 Sur l'ais en la maliere du fen Note de jeunesse; Actually Académie des Sciences, Dossien 317 (missing) (Box 3, Folder 65)
      - Paulze visit to England (Box 3, Folder 66)
        Travel diary
    - Various Archives, Libraries, and Notes
      - Lavoisier un Assignats & "Richesse Territoncale(?)" (Box 3, Folder 71)
      - American Philosophical Society 1370 #18a; Announcement of meeting of the Maison Philanthropique (11 mars 1785) Liste Lavoisier as new member, 1785 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Lavoisier Letters; Oxford (Bodl.) MS Rigard 38 (transcribed by I.B. Cohen), April 1789 (Box 3, Folder 67)
      - Perpignan Registres -- Berthelot, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 68)
      - Reims -- Biblioteque Publique Collection P. Taslié XIX, No 21; Letter from Lavoisier et. al. to Dupont, entreposens du Tabac (14 Oct 1785), 1785, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 69)
      - Lavoisier Letters -- Rouen, 1777-1792, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 70)
      - Coudercei(?) & Lagrame un Social Maiteuecter(?) (Box 3, Folder 72)
      - Terre de Freschines -- R. de Vibraye; Ac. Sci. (Box 3, Folder 73)
      - Mitouard Memoir on Distillation of Phosphorous (12 Dec 1772), December 12, 1772 (Box 3, Folder 74)
      - Ac. Sci. Lett. Et Arts-Lyon (corresponds to Ac. Sci. 72 B & C) (Box 3, Folder 75)
      - Sur la calcination des métaux dans les vaisseaux fermés -- Rozier's Journal, 1774 (Box 3, Folder 76)
      - Lavoisier on affinity (Box 3, Folder 77)
      - "Lavoisier's Concept of the Elements" chemistry colloq. Sept 13, 1973, September 13, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 78)
      - "Memoire sur la nature du principe qui se combine avec les métaux…" (from Rozier's Journal), 1775 (Box 3, Folder 79)
      - 72-J. "Les experiences fauttes sur le deamant…" (Box 3, Folder 80)
      - 1308-D "Sur l'acide du phosphore" (Box 3, Folder 81)
      - Notes on "Nomenclature Méthodique" (Box 3, Folder 82)
      - Traité Eleunaicui(?) du Chimie Noisan(?) (Box 3, Folder 83)
      - Guyion de Norveau (Box 3, Folder 84)
      - Gaspard Monge (Box 3, Folder 85)
      - Volía on Elect. of Evaporation (Box 3, Folder 86)
      - Volía and Lavoisier (& Laflere) (Box 3, Folder 87)
      - Oxides of Nitrogen (Box 3, Folder 88)
      - Lavoisier Memoire Abstrarid(?) Réflexions sur le philogistique (Box 3, Folder 89)
      - Laplace on Decomposition of Water (Box 3, Folder 90)
      - Correspondence regarding Lavoisier's arrest and death and copies of articles on Lavoisier, 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 91)
        Folder was labelled "Cartesian in England".
      - National Science Foundation Research Proposal, Memorandum on Lavoisier Manuscripts, "Development of Analytical Chemistry in the 18th Century" by F. Greenaway. (Box 3, Folder 92)
      - III. Diamond Experiment (Box 3, Folder 93)
      - Lavoisier's own summaries of intended research and recapitulation of his accomplishments. (Box 3, Folder 94)
      - Hand-written notes (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Photostat Negatives (with original numbering)
      - Mémoire: Lavoisier's claim (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Unlablelled: List of Names (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Dénonciation (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Troisieme Partie (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Essays on Atmospheric Air, Constitution of the Acids, 1783 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Richesse Territoriale: orig., 1791 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Salin et Potasse, 1789 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Elements of Chemistry in a New Systematic Order, 1793 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - L'Instruction Publique 8vo (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Mémoire de Chimie: 1st paper on calorique (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Extrait des Registres…Projet d'un nouvel Hôtel-Dieu, 1786 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Mémoires de Chimie: Tome Premier (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Richesse Territoriale reprint, 1791 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Rapport sur la Caisse D'escompte (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Réflexions sur L'instruction Publique (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Caisse d'Escompte, 1790 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Commissaires Réviseurs (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Oevres vol. II, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - L'etat des Finances, 1791 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Traité: 1st ed. 2nd issue, 1789 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Tableau des Substances Simples (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Blois, 1789 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Réponse Dénonciation (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Journal Polytype, 1786 (Box 4, Folder 25)